AGUSTIN GUERRA

888-858-6716 | agustinguerra@ufl.edu | LinkedIn | Website

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I am a highly motivated engineering professional with +5 years of experience in the transportation industry and +4 years of research experience in traffic engineering. My research interest includes optimization frameworks considering Connected and Automated Vehicles (CAVs) capabilities, real-time implementation of CAVs, traffic flow theory, microsimulation, human factors, and driving simulator studies. Currently, my PhD dissertation focuses on developing optimization algorithms for **real-time** applications considering CAVs in urban arterials. The algorithms are developed and simulated in **Python** considering the joint optimization of vehicles' trajectories and Signal Phasing and Timing (SPaT).

EDUCATION

PhD, Civil Engineering Aug. 2019 - Expected May 2023 University of Florida

Dissertation: Optimization of Traffic Performance in Signalized Arterials with CAVs

MS, Civil Engineering Aug. 2017 - May 2019

University of Kansas Lawrence, KS

Thesis: Modeling Discretionary Lane Change in a Connected Environment

BS, Civil Engineering Mar. 2008 - May 2013

Universidad Tecnologica de Panama Panama, PA

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

Aug. 2019 - Present

Gainesville, FL

University of Florida

- Develop optimization algorithms in Python for arterials considering CAVs capabilities
- Assist in the implementation of optimization algorithm for isolated intersections
- Facilitate the coordination of projects' activities to meet deadlines
- Formulated different optimization models to reduce intersections' delays (LP, IP, MILP)
- Developed heuristic methods to reduce delays in arterials (search-based algorithms)
- Developed a Python-based data pipeline to extract CAVs trajectories from connected vehicles
- · Worked on data prepossessing, and data imputation
- Evaluated machine learning algorithms to estimate the occurrence of future crashes

Master's Thesis May. 2018 - May. 2019

University of Kansas

- Conducted a driving simulator study to assess human behavior under-connected environments during Discretionary Lane-Changing (DLC) maneuvers
- Implemented a predictive DLC fuzzy logic model in a driving simulator

SUMMARY OF RESEARCH SKILLS

• Optimization modeling (LP, MIP, heuristic search), Python (Matplotlib, CPLEX, Gurobi, Numpy, Pandas, SciPy, scikit-learn, TensorFlow), signal control/traffic flow theory, human-factors, driving simulator, data pipelines, project management, research methodology & design, participant recruitment, data collection, data management, data analysis, R, SPSS, 上下X, oral presentations, Education and Public Outreach (EPO)

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Journals

[1] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Platooning Trajectory Optimization for Connected Automated Vehicles in Coordinated-Arterials. *Transportation Research Record*, 2022

Conference Proceedings

[1] L. Carvalho, **Guerra, A.**, X. Wang, P. Manjunatha, L. Elefteriadou. Simulation Platform for Testing and Evaluation of CAV Trajectory Optimization and Signal Control Algorithm Integrated with Commercial Traffic Simulator. *Proceedings of the 2022 Winter Simulation Conference*

Under Preparation

- [1] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Joint Optimization Framework to Improve Traffic Performance in Signalized Coordinated-Arterials in an Automated Environment, 2023
- [2] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Integration and Comparison of Optimization Methodologies for Connected and Automated Vehicles in a Commercial Microsimulator, 2023
- [3] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Modeling Driving Behavior in a Connected Environment. A Case Study for Signalized Arterials, 2023

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

University of Florida

Sep. 2020 – Dec. 2020

- Dictated 3 graduate lectures for the traffic flow theory course
- Explained and assisted students with traffic flow theory assignments
- Created reference material (example problems) to assist students to understand key concepts (motion of single vehicles, car-following models, shock-wave analysis, flow regimes, capacity)
- Educated on deficiencies of existing signal control strategies (detection, communication delay, computation time)
- Introduce CAVs concepts, discrete optimization methods, Python-programming language as a tool for developing optimization frameworks for CAVs
- Developed reference material for PhD students about Python, version control (git, and github), and discrete optimization

PRESENTATIONS

- [1] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefteriadou. Optimizing Signalized Coordinated Arterial Performance in a Fully Automated Environment. A Heuristic Approach. *The Transportation Research Board (TRB) 102st Annual Meeting*, 2023
- [2] **Guerra, A.**, L. Salas-Nino. Actuated Micromobility Users Presence Awareness System in Urban Arterials. *The Transportation Research Board (TRB) 102st Annual Meeting*, 2023
- [3] Elefteriadou, L., Amini, E., Carvalho, L., **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefteriadou. T3e Webinar presentation: Leveraging CAVs to Improve Traffic Operational Quality. *7th Annual UTC Conference for the Southeastern Region*, 2022
- [4] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefteriadou. A Trajectory-based Method for Platoon Formation of Connected and Automated Vehicles. *7th Annual UTC Conference for the Southeastern Region*, 2022
- [5] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Platooning Trajectory Optimization for Connected Automated Vehicles in Coordinated-Arterials. *The Transportation Research Board (TRB) 101st Annual Meeting*, 2022
- [6] Guerra, A., L. Elefeteriadou. Platooning Trajectory and Signal Phasing Optimization for Connected Automated Vehicles in Coordinated-Arterials. The Transportation Research Board (TRB) 101st Annual Meeting, 2022
- [7] **Guerra, A.**, L. Elefeteriadou. Computation Efficient Alternative for Connected Automated Vehicles Platoon Formation. *Florida Automated Vehicle (FAV) Summit*, 2021
- [8] **Guerra, A.**, M. Asgharzadeh, A. Kondyli. Discretionary Lane Changing Decisions for Connected-Vehicles Based on Fuzzy Logic. *Transportation Research Board* 99th Annual Meeting Transportation Research Board, 2020

TECHNICAL REPORTS

[1] Manjunatha P., L. Elefteriadou, M. Hunter, H. Zhou, S. Noei, **A. Guerra**, L. Carvalho, R. Favero, A. Guin, A. Saroj. Evaluation of Advanced Vehicle and Communication Technologies through Traffic Microsimulation (Project I5) *Phase II, Task 1*, 2022 (ongoing project)

LEADERSHIP/INVOLVEMENT

Founding Member and Chair of the IEEE-ITSS Student Chapter : Led the efforts to establish an IEEE Student Chapter branch of the ITSS at the University of Florida	2022 – Present
ITE University Chapter Vice President: Coordinated student seminars and ITE activities	2021 – 2022
Student Representative at the UFTI Internal Steering <u>Committee</u> : Promoted engagement activities between industry professionals and students	2020 – 2022
Media Manager at KU Fulbright Student <u>Association</u> : Led dissemination of activities promoted by the Fulbright Student Board, 2018	2018 – 2019

FELLOWSHIPS & AWARDS

 Anne Brewer Academic Scholarships: Awarded by the Intelligent Transportation Society (<u>ITS</u>) Florida Chapter 	2022
• Fulbright Fellowship: Awarded by the U.S Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs to complete a Master's Degree at the University of Kansas	2017
 Global Best Project in Roads and Highways: Awarded by the ENR for the Coastal Beltway project in Panama 	2015

PROFESSIONAL SOCIETIES

IEEE: Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers	2022 – Present
IEEE-ITSS: IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Society	2022 – Present
ASCE: American Society of Civil Engineers	2022 – Present
ITE: Institute of Transportation Engineers	2019 – Present

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Highway & Traffic Consultant

May 2019 – Aug. 2019

Panama

- Provided safety assessment for roadways, interchanges, and intersections
- Developed geometric design proposals
- · Conducted earthwork estimation for highway projects

Highway Engineer

Nov. 2012 – Aug. 2017

Louis Berger

WSP

Panama

- Developed geometric designs for proposal and as-built drawings for highway projects. Project
 portfolio comprises several projects in the Latin American region (Panama, Colombia, Honduras, and
 Peru) adding up to \$3 billion in construction amount
- Coordinated with different departments (geotechnical, hydraulic, and pavement) to meet deadlines
- · Created digital model terrain for highway projects
- Verified slope stability analysis using the Slide-Rockscience software
- Supervised and mentored drafter team with 4 people

REFERENCES

Lily Elefteriadou, PhD: Barbara Goldsby Professor, University of Florida **Alexandra Kondyli, PhD**: Associate Professor, University of Kansas **Aurora Izquierdo**: Civil Structural Engineer II, WSP

Juliana Canas: Senior Advisor, First Climate

elefter@ce.ufl.edu akondyli@ku.edu Aurora.Izquierdo@wsp.com juliana.canas-vanegas@firstclimate.com